<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="H0018386-EN">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Humboldt’s Papers</title>
            </titleStmt><editionStmt><p>: Humboldt’s Papers. In: edition humboldt digital, hg. v. Ottmar Ette. Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin. Version 11 vom 04.06.2025. URL: <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/H0018386">https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/H0018386</ref></p></editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><ref target="https://www.bbaw.de">Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</ref></publisher><pubPlace ref="https://www.geonames.org/2950159">Berlin</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence></availability><idno type="URLWeb">https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/H0018386-EN</idno><idno type="URLXML">https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/H0018386-EN.xml</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc><textClass><keywords><term>about</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body>
            <div xml:id="overview">
                <p>This module contains unpublished documents from Humboldt’s papers, held primarily
                    in the Berlin State Library and the Jagiellonian Library in Krakow. Through five
                    thematic sections, the edition offers insights into Humboldt’s research
                    practices before and after his travels. It documents ways in which he collected
                    data and connected different areas of inquiry with each other.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="t1">
                <head>Phytogeography and Life Sciences</head>
                <head type="sub">Alexander von Humboldt’s scientific programme interprets nature as
                    a harmonious unity of all phenomena, substances and living beings. </head>
                <ab>Editing period: 2015–2019<lb/><ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/themen/biowissenschaften.xql?l=en">To the results</ref></ab>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="TS_1klein.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Humboldt started his investigations in the field of plant geography by asking
                    questions about the connection between the history of plants and that of
                    mankind. During his American journey, Humboldt developed the concept of plant
                    physiognomy: Main morphological forms determine the character of different types
                    of vegetation. In the “Tableau physique des Andes et pays voisins”, which was
                    also designed during the journey, the geography of plants is part of a global
                    geoscientific research project. During the 1820s, Humboldt developed the
                    numerical method of botanical arithmetic. This concept, as well as
                    the–ultimately abandoned–project of a <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/themen/detail.xql?id=H0002731&amp;l=en">new edition of his “Essai sur la Géographie des plantes”</ref>, were part
                    of a broader vision of plant geography on a global scale. </p>
                <p>Humboldt’s papers contain numerous unpublished manuscripts and correspondences
                    (including those with <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/briefe/index.xql?person=H0006403&amp;l=en">Karl Ludwig Willdenow</ref> and <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/briefe/index.xql?person=H0001517&amp;l=en">Carl Sigismund Kunth</ref>) on plant geography, which were published in
                    2016–2018 in the <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi>. A curated
                    selection was published in 2020 as Volume 1 of <ref target="https://www.springer.com/series/16348">Series III "Forschungen im
                        Umfeld der Reise"</ref> of the <ref target="https://www.springer.com/series/16345"><hi rendition="#i">edition
                                humboldt print</hi></ref> entitled <ref target="https://www.springer.com/gp/book/9783476049643"><hi rendition="#i">Geographie der Pflanzen: Unveröffentlichte Schriften aus dem
                                        Nachlass</hi></ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="t2">
                <head>Scientific Travels</head>
                <head type="sub">How did Humboldt motivate and influence contemporary research
                    trips?</head>
                <ab>Editing period: 2019–2024<lb/><ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/themen/forschungsreisen.xql?l=en">To the
                        results</ref></ab>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="TS_2klein.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Virtually all traveling naturalists of the time referred to Humboldt and his
                    travel account. Humboldt, in return, advised and supported many travelers.
                    Research institutions compiled travel instructions, which also corresponded to
                    Humboldt’s ideal of comprehensive collection and note-taking practices. At the
                    same time, however, the natural sciences – and travelers with them – were
                    becoming increasingly specialised. The result was a tension between (Humboldt’s)
                    ideal of traveling and how travel was being practised, which Humboldt and others
                    saw critically and commented on.</p>
                <head type="sub">How did the relationship develop between the travelers and the
                    scholars, administrators and curators who stayed at home?</head>
                <p>Due to an increasing separation between researchers who collected data in the
                    field and those who scientifically evaluated the objects and data at home,
                    Humboldt often communicated between travelers and their patrons, pre-published
                    findings on behalf of absent researchers and mediated the exchange, lending and
                    sale of collection objects throughout Europe. In this sense, <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/themen/forschungsreisen.xql?l=en">the
                        thematic section Scientific Travels</ref> is connected to the history of
                    objects and follows the traces of Humboldt’s work as a mediator – for example in
                    Berlin collections.</p>
                <p><ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0016785?l=en">Christian Gottfried
                        Ehrenberg’s Diary of the Russian-Siberian Journey</ref> with Humboldt
                    (1829), which contains numerous references to zoological
                    and <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/pflanzen/index.xql?id=H0016785&amp;l=en">botanical specimens sent</ref> to collections in Berlin and Paris, has
                    already been published in 2019 as part of the <hi rendition="#i">edition
                        humboldt digital</hi>.</p>
                <p>During his American journey, Humboldt recognized a connection between aesthetics
                    and science. His <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/X0000017">correspondence with Johann Moritz Rugendas</ref>
                    shows how he communicated his concept to a new generation of landscape painters
                    traveling to America.</p>
                <p><ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/briefe/index.xql?person=H0015552&amp;l=en">Adolph</ref>, <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/briefe/index.xql?person=H0015557&amp;l=en">Hermann</ref>
                    and <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/briefe/index.xql?person=H0015556&amp;l=en">Robert</ref> Schlagintweit’s trip to India and the Himalayas (1854–1858)
                    was the last scientific project Humboldt supported by means of his reputation
                    and influence. The brothers undertook their expedition at a time of profound
                    epistemological transformation in the areas of field research and the study of
                    foreign cultures. Humboldt’s correspondence with the Schlagintweit brothers
                    documents a paradigm shift in media history from natural painting to
                    photography. The extensive collections of the Schlagintweits were initially
                    intended, with Alexander von Humboldt's support, for a planned Indian Museum in
                    Berlin's Monbijou Palace, but soon became the object of dispute between British
                    colonial authorities and the Prussian museum administration.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="t3">
                <head>The knowledge of the earth</head>
                <head type="sub">Humboldt's geoscientific research encompassed the modern
                    disciplines of mineralogy, geology, meteorology, climatology and
                    geophysics.</head>
                <ab>Editing period: 2024–2027<lb/><ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/themen/wissen-von-der-erde.xql?l=en">To the
                        results</ref></ab>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="TS_3klein.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>He compared the structure of the earth’s crust as well as the strike and dip of
                    mountains and volcanic arcs across the globe to establish common patterns and
                    understand the laws of nature. Humboldt pursued the same goal in his
                    investigations of the atmosphere and the global distribution of mean temperature
                    zones.</p>
                <p>Humboldt's papers in the Berlin State Library contain numerous unpublished
                    manuscripts, which can shed new light on Humboldt's geognostic hypotheses:
                    Immediately after the American Journey he carried out chemical experiments on
                    the composition of the atmosphere with Louis-Jacques Thénard and Joseph
                    Gay-Lussac (“Absorption de l’oxygène par les terres humectées”; “Expériments sur
                    l’air atmosphérique”, <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-HS-1280521">Papers Large Box
                        8</ref>). These experiments can be seen as a continuation of his
                    observations on air purity and the assumed connection with the spread of
                    epidemic diseases (especially yellow fever), which Humboldt had recorded a few
                    months earlier in New Spain and Cuba (“C'est mon cahier de la Havane intitulé
                    sur la salubrité de l'air”, 28 fols., <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-HS-2849282">Vol. 1 of the Krakow
                        Papers</ref>).</p>
                <p>During the 1820s, Humboldt composed numerous manuscripts in preparation of his
                    <hi rendition="#i">Geognostische Versuche über die Ausbreitung der
                        Gebirgsarten in beiden Erdhälften</hi> (1823). The “Examen des hypothèses
                    géologiques considérées dans le rapport de leur concordance avec les principes
                    de la Mécanique, de la Physique et de la Chimie” (over thirty pages long) (<ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-HS-1035140">Papers Large Box
                        5</ref>) deals among other things with writings on thermodynamics by Joseph
                    Fourier and Siméon Denis Poisson. The <ref target="http://archiv.bbaw.de/archiv/archivbestaende/abteilung-nachlasse/nachlasse/humboldt_alexander">archives of the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</ref>
                    hold a copy of the French edition of the <hi rendition="#i">Geognostische
                        Versuche, </hi>interleaved with numerous handwritten notes. </p>
                <p>Following the Russian-Siberian journey, Humboldt intensively dealt with the
                    geology and climatology of the Asian continent. A first result was an Academy
                    lecture held in January 1831 in Paris, entitled “Sur quelques phénomènes
                    physiques et géognostiques de l'Asie au nord de parallèle de 50 degrés” (<ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-HS-1035153">Papers Large Box
                        5</ref>), which will be published for the first time in the <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi>. Here, too, Humboldt's research
                    reveals itself to be a science on the move: “La description du globe n'est point
                    une science stationnaire” [The physical description of the Earth is not a
                    stationary science].</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="t4">
                <head>Cartography and the history of discovery</head>
                <head type="sub">During his American journey Humboldt refined geographical knowledge
                    of the continent through astronomical positioning and first cartographic
                    preliminary drawings.</head>
                <ab>In planning<lb/><ref target="https://humboldt.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/work/?lang=en#toggle-id-4">Humboldt's Papers</ref></ab>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="TS_4klein.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The two atlases of the American travel account are based on earlier map series by
                    American and European cartographers, which Humboldt used as points of reference.
                    While working on his atlases, Humboldt was in contact with American (José Manuel
                    Restrepo, Joaquín Acosta) and European (Adrian-Hubert Brué, Pierre Lapie,
                    Jean-Baptiste Joseph Delambre) cartographers, draughtsmen and engravers.This
                    exchange is richly documented in <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-42736">Volume 7</ref> and
                    <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-42737">Volume 8</ref> of
                    the Krakow papers and will be comprehensively covered in this thematic
                    section.</p>
                <p>As a historian of the geographical exploration of the American continent by
                    Europeans, Humboldt recognised the value of the early modern maps of America as
                    historical sources. His investigations into the history of cartography, as
                    documented in the manuscripts and sketches of <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-42738">Volume 9</ref> of the
                    Krakow papers, are another focus of the thematic section.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="t5">
                <head>History of Globalization and Anthropology</head>
                <head type="sub">“All are in equal measure ordained for liberty”</head>
                <ab>In planning<lb/><ref target="https://humboldt.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/work/?lang=en#toggle-id-4">Humboldt's Papers</ref></ab>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="TS_5klein.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>Documents, transcripts, notes and correspondence regarding a "history of the
                    world view", as Humboldt himself names various envelopes, can be found
                    especially in the <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-12815">Large Box 8</ref> of the Berlin papers. It contains materials on the
                    natural philosophy of the Egyptians, Greeks and Chinese, on the prehistory of
                    the Phoenicians, on the history of Sanskrit and Indian philosophy as well as on
                    the early history of globalization in the context of the European conquest of
                    the American continent.</p>
                <p>Humboldt’s historical interpretation of the age of European discoveries and the
                    early phase of Ibero-American colonialism has also left its traces in the Krakow
                    estate. Adding to the materials from the thematic section on the history of
                    discovery and cartography, Humboldt proves to have a scholarly interest in
                    American linguistic diversity. Here, the research interests of the two Humboldt
                    Brothers correspond. Alexander collects materials on North and Mesoamerican
                    linguistic and cultural history as well as information on the archaeology of
                    early American civilizations, which he then compares to the history of the
                    so-called Orient (above all Egypt) and the cultures of East Asia.</p>
                <p>In the first volume of his <hi rendition="#i">Kosmos</hi>, Humboldt coined a now
                    well-known sentence that emphasized the unity of the human race: "In maintaining
                    the unity of the human kind, we at the same time repudiate all the
                    unsatisfactory assumptions of higher and lower races of men. There are races of
                    men more flexible, more highly polished, through mental culture more ennobled,
                    but none naturally more noble. All are in equal measure ordained for liberty;
                    for liberty which in ruder conditions of society appertains to the individual,
                    which in more polished state, in civil life and among men in the enjoyment of
                    political institutions, is the right of the community." Humboldt’s findings on
                    the cultures of humankind, as expressed for example in the <hi rendition="#i">Vues des Cordillères et monumens des peuples indigènes de l'Amérique</hi>
                    published in 1810–1813, as well as his studies on slavery and the plantation
                    economy, which were initiated in particular by his experiences on the American
                    journey, are oriented towards this conviction. Both the Krakow (especially <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-42729">volumes 1–3</ref>) and
                    Berlin papers (especially <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-12629">Large Box 2</ref> and
                    <ref target="http://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-BF-12819">Large Box
                        13</ref>) are an indispensable source for this research focus.</p>
            </div>
    </body></text>
</TEI>