<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="H0021024">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Digital Methodology</title>
                <title type="sub">An introduction to data modeling, technologies and interfaces in the edition humboldt digital</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Dumont</surname>
                        <forename>Stefan</forename>
                    </persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt><editionStmt><p>Dumont, Stefan: Digital Methodology .  An introduction to data modeling, technologies and interfaces in the edition humboldt digital. In: edition humboldt digital, hg. v. Ottmar Ette. Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin. Version 11 vom 04.06.2025. URL: <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/">https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/</ref></p></editionStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <relatedItem target="H0016212" type="translation" xml:lang="de"/>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><publisher><ref target="https://www.bbaw.de">Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</ref></publisher><pubPlace ref="https://www.geonames.org/2950159">Berlin</pubPlace><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence></availability><idno type="URLWeb">https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/</idno><idno type="URLXML">https://edition-humboldt.de/v11/.xml</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc><textClass><keywords><term>about</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body>
            <div>
                <head type="h2">Data model</head>
                <p>The following section provides an initial overview of the data model of <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi>. The comprehensive
                    documentation of the data model can be found in the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/richtlinien/index.html">Editionsrichtlinien</ref> (german only).</p>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Historical sources</head>
                    <p>The metadata and texts of the edited manuscripts (travel journals, letters and
                        documents) are encoded according to the guidelines of the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Text Encoding Initiative
                            (TEI)</ref>. By using ediarum.BASE.edit, the <ref target="http://deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/">Base format of
                            the German Text Archive (DTABf)</ref> (<bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/47JJACHG">Haaf/Geyken/Wiegand 2015</bibl>) is
                        largely used, which has been extended for the encoding of handwritten texts,
                        <bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/EACNDF7P">(Haaf/Thomas 2018)</bibl>. For a few
                        project-specific concerns, additions and extensions to the tagset were made
                        that are compliant with the TEI guidelines. These extensions relate in
                        particular to project-specific requirements arising from the material, such
                        as the tagging of measurements as well as inserted or appended notes. However, the
                        extensions has been made in a way, that these
                        follow as closely as possible the systematics of the DTABf. Thus, in many cases, instead of adding new elements or attributes, attribute values were added. </p>
                    <p>All names of persons, places and institutions as well as bibliographic references in the
                        source texts (and their metadata) are linked to their respective index
                        entries.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Paratexts</head>
                    <p>All other texts, such as the introductory research articles on the diary
                        fragment <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/H0002922?l=en">"Isle de Cube.
                            Antilles en général,"</ref> were also recorded in TEI-XML according to
                        the Base format of the German Text Archive.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Indexes</head>
                    <p>The indexes on <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/personen/index.xql?l=en">persons</ref>, <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/orte/index.xql?l=en">places</ref> and <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/einrichtungen/index.xql?l=en">institutions</ref> as well as the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/glossar/index.xql?l=en">glossary</ref> are edited and held in TEI-XML. Each entry has its own
                        unique and permanent ID. In addition to the basic data of an entry, a short
                        description is also provided. </p>
                    <p>The entries are also provided with one or more URIs from different authority
                        files, if an entry exists there. This makes it possible to identify persons,
                        places and institutions <hi rendition="#i">across projects</hi>, both in ehd
                        itself and when using the APIs and data publication (see also <bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/W4L92XBE">Stadler 2012</bibl> on authority files
                        in editions). For person entries, the GND is primarily used, alternatively
                        or additionally also <ref target="https://viaf.org/">VIAF</ref>. For places,
                        on the other hand, URIs from the free geographic database <ref target="https://www.geonames.org">GeoNames</ref> are used, since this
                        achieves a high level of coverage worldwide and entries can be added
                        by the project itself if necessary. Thus, a few localities missing in
                        GeoNames (such as the former locations of the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0000531?l=en">Berlin Observatory</ref>)
                        were added there. </p>
                    <p>Furthermore, the project retrodigitized the index entries of 25
                        editions (corrspondence, documents, diary excerpts) of Alexander von Humboldt
                        research published between 1973 and 2016 and made them available in the digital index. 
                        These index information of the printed editions is part of
                        the series first published by the Akademie-Verlag and finally by De Gruyter
                            <ref target="https://www.degruyter.com/view/serial/BAHF-B"><hi rendition="#i">Beiträge zur Alexander-von-Humboldt-Forschung</hi></ref>, 
                        edited by the Alexander-von-Humboldt-Forschungsstelle
                        (1970-2014) of the BBAW. </p>
                    <p>Links between index entries and the edited materials are automatically
                        generated from the database using the ehd-ID.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">Humboldt's token</head>
                        <p>On manuscripts of Alexander von Humboldt sometimes so-called "Siglen" (tokens) can
                            be found, i.e. combinations of 1-2 characters (e.g. "Ad") that relate different documents,
                            letters and diary entries to each other. These token were not only
                            transcribed, but also entered into a separate TEI-XML register and
                            linked to it from the text passages. In this way, the relationships can
                            also be traced in the digital edition.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <anchor type="target" xml:id="pflanzenregister"/>
                        <head type="h4">Plant index</head>
                        <p>For the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/pflanzen/index.xql?l=en">plant index</ref>, <hi rendition="#i">no</hi> separate entries are created in a TEI-XML
                            index file (as with the other indexes). Instead, the scientific
                            plant names in the edited texts are annotated in the texts using the appropriate TEI
                            encoding, normalized if necessary, and then retrieved automatically. The
                            plant index is thus created completely dynamically. Each distinct
                            plant name has a list of references to the texts and is
                            automatically linked to various taxonomic databases (see below, section
                                <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0016212/globalnames">Global indexes for scientific
                                names</ref>).</p>
                        <p>Since version 10 (2024), however, the actual dynamic plant register is also automatically created as TEI-XML (including internal and external references). This means that the plant register can also be included in the data publication in the future.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">Drawings and sketches</head>
                        <p>Since version 9 of the <hi rendition="#i">ehd</hi>, a virtual "index" provides an overview of drawings
                            and sketches from Humboldt's or other contemporary hand in the edited
                            texts. Similar to the plant index, it is compiled automatically from the
                            illustrations marked with <hi rend="code">figure.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">Bibliography</head>
                        <p>The <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/literatur/index.xql?l=en">bibliography</ref> of the edition is maintained in the literature
                            management software Zotero. The publicly viewable <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/667230/">Zotero group</ref>
                            allows collaborative maintenance of the data and can be accessed by all
                            interested parties - also in various citation styles and export formats
                            (see below).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Documentation</head>
                    <p>The documentation of the data model is done in <ref target="http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/dita/v1.3/dita-v1.3-part3-all-inclusive.html">DITA</ref>, more precisely in the DITA files of <ref target="https://www.ediarum.org/docs/ediarum.BASE.manual/">ediarum.BASE.manual</ref>. This way synergies are used as well as
                        specifications or modifications compared to the data model of
                        ediarum.BASE.edit are documented. DITA (and not ODD) was chosen to enable
                        this combination of ediarum.BASE.manual and the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/richtlinien/index.html">guidelines
                            of edition humboldt digital</ref>. Furthermore, the internal DITA
                        documentation includes not only the coding guidelines based on the concrete
                        material, but also the <hi rendition="#i">operating
                            instructions</hi> for the editors in ediarum.AVHR.edit.</p>
                    <p>The edition guidelines each refer to the corresponding parts of the DTABf
                        documentation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Schema</head>
                    <p>While the schema was initially formulated in RelaxNG, it is
                        now maintained as a TEI ODD file <bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/QGGN2BZP">(Viglianti 2019</bibl>) (from which, however, RNG derivatives continue
                        to be created). It is derived using ODD chaining from the
                        ediarum.BASE.schema, which in turn is derived from the DTABf. This makes it
                        possible to maintain and track the respective changes to the next "higher"
                        schema at each level (ediarum, edition humboldt digital etc.). The schema (as TEI-ODD file as well as RNG)
                        are published on <ref target="https://github.com/telota/ediarum.AVHR.data-model">GitHub</ref>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="h2">Software &amp; Technologies</head>
                <p>The publication <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi> is created in
                        <hi rendition="#i">ediarum</hi>. The <ref target="https://www.ediarum.org/">digital working environment <hi rendition="#i">ediarum</hi></ref> is a solution developed since 2012 by the <ref target="http://www.bbaw.de/telota">DH initiative TELOTA</ref>,
                    that allows scholars to edit transcriptions of manuscripts, comments, and
                    index entries in TEI-compliant XML, add a critical apparatus and notes, and
                    then publish them on the web and as PDFs (<bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/ZFPTSUNP">Dumont/Fechner 2014</bibl>). <hi rendition="#i">Ediarum</hi> consists of several software modules. For the input and editing
                    of data, edition humboldt digital uses the module <hi rendition="#i">ediarum.BASE.edit</hi>, which - as is usual with ediarum - is supplemented
                    by a project-specific module <hi rendition="#i">ediarum.AVHR.edit</hi> for the edition humboldt digital. 
                    The module ediarum.REGISTER.edit is used to create and maintain the index
                    entries. An exception is the bibliography, which is maintained in the literature
                    management software Zotero. For this, <hi rendition="#i">ediarum.DB</hi> offers
                    an interface for synchronization.</p>
                <p>The data is first stored in a Git (<bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/SUJV58N2">Fechner/Klappenbach/Lampert 2025</bibl>) and in a second stage (automated)
                    in an instance of the free XML database <ref target="http://www.exist-db.org">existdb</ref>, the module <hi rendition="#i">ediarum.DB</hi> is used to
                    manage the data. Existdb serves at the same time - together with the web server
                    Jetty - also as basis of the digital edition, which was realized with XQuery,
                    XSLT and XPath and in the meantime in an eXistdb App in accordance with the
                    EXPath packaging specifications, which simplifies Deployment and development.
                    For the search functions, the Lucene-based faceting, available since eXistdb
                    5.0, is used. In addition, the edition has several specially programmed caches
                    that increase performance, especially for complex queries. For the display of
                    facsimiles, drawings and illustrations the software <ref target="http://digilib.sourceforge.net/">digilib</ref>, developed at the MPI
                    for the History of Science, is used.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Layout &amp; Web Design</head>
                <p>The design of <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi> originates from
                    drafts that the author originally developed in 2014 for the project
                    "Schleiermacher in Berlin 1808-1834". Due to the similarity of the
                    edition type and the source genres, the designs could be reused
                    and further developed for the ehd. </p>
                <p>The design is based on principles of "flat design", i.e. simplicity, minimalism
                    and a strong focus on typography. Especially the latter is a central point,
                    since this digital edition is about one thing above all: text. Therefore, an
                        Antiqua<hi rendition="#i">(PT Serif</hi>) was chosen as the main typeface,
                    which has a "true" italic cut. It is accompanied by a grotesque <hi rendition="#i">(PT Sans</hi>) from the same typeface family, which is mainly used in
                    subnavigations, smaller text and meta information. These <hi rendition="#i">classic</hi> typographical conventions, as far as they could be reasonably
                    transferred to the digital medium web, were also taken into account in the
                    further design. For example, a flexible text width oriented to the width of the
                    viewport was dispensed - in favor of a fixed one that corresponds roughly
                    to the typographically recommended line length.</p>
                <p>The design approach also does not use a dedicated page header: in order to
                    give the texts as much space as possible, only a low navigation bar was placed at the top, 
                    which is clearly visible thanks to the black color. The page
                    header is taken up by the document title or title of the individual page instead
                    of the website title and sponsor etc. logos (which were quite common in 2014). At the
                    same time, this space also provides room for further meta information and
                    sub-navigation (chronological scrolling between letters; sub-section navigation;
                    letters in the index, etc.).</p>
                <p>The design has to master two challenges: On the one hand, the abundance of
                    different text types (edited letters, travel journals, documents; research contributions
                    and indexes) and information that need to be accommodated. Here the design of the ehd
                    follows the principle not to show everything immediately, but to fade in certain
                    information only on user interaction. There should always be enough white space
                    to let the eye rest or to group and prioritize the different information in a
                    meaningful way. A second challenge was (and still is) to adapt the design to the
                    changing requirements and the constantly growing amount of material and
                    information. For such a long-running academy project (2015-2032), not every type
                    of information and function was foreseeable at the beginning. Thus, the design
                    has also been adapted again and again - from the introduction of a
                    sub-navigation, to the redesign of the homepage and the introduction of
                    page-based text and facsimile display, to the ever more in-depth and complexly
                    distinguished edited texts. This is sometimes more and sometimes less
                    well done.</p>
                <p>The implementation of the design in HTML uses the <ref target="https://960.gs">960
                        Grid System</ref> and relied heavy on CSS. Javascript
                    is only used for special - if necessary replaceable - functions of the
                    interface; the generation of the HTML pages is thus largely server-side to
                    facilitate archiving in the Web Archive or the BBAW Web Archive.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="h2">External data &amp; web services used</head>
                <figure facs="https://digilib.bbaw.de/digilib/Scaler?fn=projects/avhr/Projekt/ehd_network_2023.png&amp;dw=958&amp;dh=483">
                    <figDesc>The networked edition humboldt digital. Simultaneously published in the
                        poster "The networked edition humboldt digital". DH2023 in Graz. Abstract:
                        https: <ref target="https://zenodo.org/record/8107834">//zenodo.org/record/8107834.</ref></figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>For the digital edition, data from third-party projects were reused or external
                    web services were used in several places.</p>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Cascaded Analysis Broker of the German Text Archive
                        (DTA::CAB)</head>
                    <p>The normal search can be extended by a function that also finds historical
                        spellings and other word forms. For this purpose, the edited texts are
                        linguistically analyzed and annotated using the <ref target="http://kaskade.dwds.de/demo/cab/">DTA::CAB web service</ref>.
                        Among other things, all words are lemmatized so that searches can be
                        performed on the basis of this lemma. DTA::CAB was developed by Bryan Jurish
                        as part of the <ref target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de">German Text
                            Archive</ref>.</p>
                    <p>For more information, see the <ref target="https://kaskade.dwds.de/~moocow/software/DTA-CAB/">documentation</ref> or <bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/92M2WH4K">Jurish
                            2012</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Humboldt's writings in the German Text Archive.</head>
                    <p>In the German Text Archive, over <ref target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/api/pnd/118554700">180</ref>
                        of <ref target="http://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/api/pnd/118554700">Alexander von Humboldt's writings</ref> are available TEI-XML encoded
                        in full text. A function has been implemented in the chronology that
                        displays or searches the title data of these writings. For this purpose, the
                            <ref target="http://kaskade.dwds.de/dstar/dta/">D* OpenSearch API</ref>
                            (dazu<ref target="https://kaskade.dwds.de/dstar/dta/osd.xml">:OpenSearch
                            Description</ref>) provided by the German Text Archive is used. Thus,
                        the full texts of Humboldt's writings can not only be displayed, but also
                        searched: The search function allows to specify the number of hits and to
                        link directly to the hit list.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Digitized bibliography on avhumboldt.de</head>
                    <p>Within the portal avhumboldt.de a <ref target="http://www.avhumboldt.de/?p=6769">digitized b</ref> ibliography
                        of Alexander von Humboldt's independently published writings has been
                        provided since 2009 under the direction of Tobias Kraft. The data of this
                        bibliography was converted into XML and integrated into the database of <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital to</hi> be displayed in the
                        chronology.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">correspSearch</head>
                    <p>The web service <ref target="http://correspSearch.net">correspSearch</ref>
                        aggregates machine-readable letter indexes from printed or digital letter
                        editions and makes them centrally searchable (Dumont et al 2023; <bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/T2AXRQ5N">Dumont 2018</bibl>). In addition, it
                        provides an <ref target="http://correspsearch.net/de/api.html">interface</ref> that also enables automated retrieval of these data and
                        reuse in one's own programs. Since Humboldt's correspondence<bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/UGSUKML5">(Schwarz 2018</bibl>) was already
                        considered too extensive to be edited in a complete edition in the 1960s, it
                        has since been published scattered in individual correspondence editions or
                        even essays (especially in the journal <ref target="https://www.hin-online.de">Humboldt im Netz</ref>)<bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/HKNVP8BH">(Schröder 2008</bibl>). In
                        correspSearch, almost all of the more than 6000 <ref target="https://correspsearch.net/de/suche.html?s=http://d-nb.info/gnd/118554700">published letters to and from Alexander von Humboldt</ref> have been
                        brought together for the first time and made searchable for researchers. </p>
                    <p>In <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi>, this data is queried via
                        the API of correspSearch in two places: firstly, in the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/chronologie/index.xql?jahr=&amp;cs=on&amp;offset=51">chronology</ref> (if this option is activated accordingly); this brings
                        together the more than 1600 entries on Humboldt's life with his published
                        correspondence. On the other hand, the correspSearch API is queried in the
                        individual view of a letter under "Explore letter network". There, letters
                        from and to Alexander Humboldt from other editions are queried in order to
                        make visible with which other correspondence partners Humboldt still had
                        contact in the respective period. In addition, the letters received and sent
                        by the respective correspondence partner during the corresponding period are
                        displayed - the query is based on the GND or VIAF URI stored in the
                        register. In this way, the "extended correspondence context" of the letter
                        network is made visible<bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/HW747AF8">(Dumont
                            2023</bibl>). This function was originally prototyped in the <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi> on the basis of XQuery and
                        then newly implemented in the DFG project correspSearch as a <ref target="https://correspsearch.net/de/csLink.html">freely reusable
                            Javascript widget <hi rendition="#i">csLink</hi></ref> (Müller-Laackman
                        / Dumont 2022). This is also used in the meantime in <hi rendition="#i">ehd</hi>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Practices of the Monarchy: Court Calendar</head>
                    <p>Also integrated into the chronology are <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/chronologie/index.xql?jahr=1848&amp;hofkalendarium=on&amp;l=en">events at the Prussian court in which Alexander von Humboldt
                            participated</ref> and which are recorded in the <ref target="https://actaborussica.bbaw.de/P0006298">court calendar</ref>,
                        which is part of the publication "Practices of the Monarchy". For this
                        purpose, the TEI-XML data of the Hofkalendarium are transferred to <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi> and the personal mentions
                        are mapped to the ehd register using the GND URIs (if available, otherwise
                        they link to the register entries of <hi rendition="#i">Praktiken der
                            Monarchie</hi>). </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">GeoNames &amp; OpenStreetMap.</head>
                    <p>The places and institution locations listed in the register are usually
                        linked to a URI of the free geographic database <ref target="https://www.geonames.org"><hi rendition="#i">GeoNames</hi></ref>
                        provided. This allows the locations to be identified across projects, which
                        greatly simplifies subsequent use of the data. The GeoNames URI is also used
                        to obtain the geographic coordinates, on the basis of which a corresponding
                        map can be displayed with the location and institution entries using the
                        free map service <ref target="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</ref>. This is especially helpful for smaller locations
                        of Alexander von Humboldt's various travels.</p>
                    <p>With version 11 of edition humboldt digital, the geodata-based functions in
                        the place index have been expanded: an <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/orte/map.xql?l=en">interactive world map</ref> now provides an overview of all places
                        listed in the place index. In addition, neighboring places that are also
                        listed in the index are displayed within a radius of approx. 30 km of an
                        individual place in its index entry - both on the map and as a list with
                        distance information (example: <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/register/orte/detail.xql?id=H0019176&amp;l=en">Zmeëvka</ref>).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Common Norm File &amp; BEACON</head>
                    <p>Based on the URI noted in an entry of the register of persons from the <ref target="http://www.dnb.de/DE/Standardisierung/GND/gnd_node.html"><hi rendition="#i">Common Norm File</hi></ref> (GND), further data can
                        be obtained via the GND web service "Entity Facts". Thus, with the help of
                        the "Entity Facts", on the one hand, portraits are faded in directly from
                        Wikimedia Commons, and on the other hand, information on (family,
                        friendship, etc.) relationships between persons is obtained. These are also
                        automatically evaluated in the ehd on the basis of the GND URIs and then
                        displayed to the users accordingly (see, for example, the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0015944?l=en">entry on Samuel Thomas
                            Soemmerring</ref>). </p>
                    <p>The GND-ID also allows linking to other editions, encyclopedias and projects
                        that are <hi rendition="#i">digitally</hi> relevant in the subject area of
                            <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt</hi>. The BEACON interfaces of these
                        projects are used for this purpose. For example, it is possible to identify
                        thematic overlaps with other projects of the <ref target="http://zentrumpreussen.bbaw.de/">Center Prussia-Berlin at the
                            BBAW</ref> via the links in the register data and to make them available
                        for research (example <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0012068?l=en">Wilhelm von Humboldt</ref> or <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0015568?l=en">Friedrich
                            Schleiermacher</ref>). But also external offers, such as <ref target="https://www.deutschestextarchiv.de/kosmos/">Hidden Kosmos</ref>
                        or <ref target="https://www.deutsche-biographie.de/">Die deutsche
                            Biographie</ref> are linked automatically in this way.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <anchor type="target" xml:id="globalnames"/>
                    <head type="h3">Global indices for scientific names</head>
                    <p>In the plant index<ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/H0016212/pflanzenregister">(see above</ref>),
                        various web services and APIs are used to link scientific plant names from
                        texts of <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt</hi> to matching entries from
                        taxonomic databases in an automated <hi rendition="#i">digital</hi> way.
                        Using the <ref target="https://resolver.globalnames.org/">Global Names
                            Resolver</ref> web service, the Plant Register links scientific names to
                        entries in the <ref target="https://eol.org/">Encylopedia of Life</ref>,
                            <ref target="https://www.tropicos.org/">Tropicos - Missouri Botanical
                            Garden</ref>, <ref target="https://www.ipni.org/">The International
                            Plant Names Index</ref> (IPNI). In addition, the <ref target="https://www.catalogueoflife.org/">Catalogue of Life</ref>, the
                            <ref target="https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/">Biodiversity Heritage
                            Library</ref>, and the <ref target="https://www.gbif.org/">Global
                            Biodiversity Information Facility</ref> are queried using their own
                        interfaces and are also linked. Other databases may be added in the future,
                        provided they have appropriate technical interfaces.</p>
                    <p>The query of the different databases and automated linking is based on the
                        scientific plant name, which is coded accordingly in the edited text and
                        normalized if necessary.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="h2">Data provision &amp; APIs</head>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Licensing</head>
                    <p><hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi> not only reuses external
                        data and web services, but in turn makes its data available under the free
                            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative
                            Commons license CC BY-SA 4.0</ref> via an interface and as an
                        independent <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13752841">data
                            publication</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h4">TEI-XML interface</head>
                    <p>All edited texts, research articles and chronology and register entries of
                            <hi rendition="i">edition humboldt digital</hi> can be retrieved via the
                        TEI-XML interface <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.2/tei-xml.xql">http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.2/tei-xml.xql</ref> (note version
                            1<hi rendition="#b">.2</hi>). </p>
                    <p>When called without the parameters, a list of all data with title and
                        permalink of the respective current version is offered. When retrieved with
                        the <hi rend="code">type</hi> parameter, a list of the respective document
                        types is generated (see table below). When retrieved with parameter <hi rend="code">id</hi>, the respective document is output.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h5">Parameter <hi rend="code">type</hi></head>
                        <table rend="drawn" rows="2" cols="2">
                            <row role="label">
                                <cell>Values</cell>
                                <cell>Description</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="code">[not set]</hi></cell>
                                <cell>all records in the person register; set by default unless
                                    otherwise specified</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="code">correspondents</hi></cell>
                                <cell>all correspondents</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="code">personsMentioned</hi></cell>
                                <cell>all persons mentioned</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h2">data publication</head>
                    <p>All edited texts, research contributions as well as the index of persons,
                        places, institutions and sigles are also published digitally as a complete
                        TEI-XML dataset of the edition humboldt. For this purpose, the texts and
                        entries are not simply exported from the eXistdb, but are retrieved with the
                        help of a XQuery script via the TEI-XML-API 2.0 of <hi rendition="#i">ehd</hi>, so that the data image matches that of the data accessible
                        via the API. This makes use of the enrichments that take place there (e.g.
                        GNDs; URIs instead of IDs), the harmonizations to the DTABf as well as the
                        division of the register lists into individual TEI-XML files. In the
                        process, the directory structure will also be changed so that the data is
                        organized by type (i.e. letters, diaries, research contributions, register
                        entries, etc.).</p>
                    <p>For initial purely technical versioning, the TEI XML files retrieved in this
                        way are played into a Git repository, which is also available <ref target="https://github.com/telota/edition-humboldt-digital">for public
                            viewing on GitHub</ref>. After a check and completion with the TEI-XML
                        schema of ehd (as RNG), the dataset is exported from there to Zenodo to be
                        freely available there in a long-term archived form: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13752841">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13752841</ref> (canonical URL, always links to the last version of the dataset).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head type="h3">Further APIs</head>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">OAI-PMH</head>
                        <p>The metadata of the edited texts as well as the research articles
                            are provided via the interface <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.1/oai-pmh.xql?verb=Identify">http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.1/oai-pmh.xql?verb=Identify</ref> according to
                            the <ref target="https://www.openarchives.org/pmh/">Protocoll for
                                Metadata Harvesting of the Open Archive Initiative</ref>. Thus,
                            these texts are also automatically referenced in the <ref target="https://www.base-search.net/">Bielefeld Academic Search
                                Enginge (BASE)</ref>. As a metadata format for OAI-PMH, only Dublin
                            Core is currently supported.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">CMIF interface</head>
                        <p>Via this interface the correspondence metadata of all letters available
                            in this edition can be retrieved in the <ref target="https://correspsearch.net/de/dokumentation.html">Correspondence Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF)</ref>. As a
                            result, the letters edited in this edition will be referenced in
                            correspSearch.</p>
                        <p>The API already supports some extensions of <ref target="https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF/blob/main/proposals/CMIFv2_proposal.md">CMIF v2</ref>, such as the persons
                                <hi rendition="#i">mentioned</hi> and the URL to the corresponding
                            TEI-XML full text. The latter makes it possible to find these letters in
                            the full text search of correspSearch <ref target="https://correspsearch.net/de/suche.html?q=fieber*">(example: “fieber*”)</ref>.</p>
                        <p>URL: <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.2/cmif.xql">http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.2/cmif.xql</ref></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">BEACON files</head>
                        <p>The persons available in the ehd data stock and marked with the <ref target="http://www.dnb.de/DE/Standardisierung/GND/gnd_node.html">GND-URI</ref> can be retrieved via <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.1/beacon.xql">http://edition-humboldt.de/api/v1.1/beacon.xql</ref> as a list in
                                <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:BEACON">BEACON
                                format</ref> and can be linked automatically in external digital
                            offers. It is possible to limit the list to persons who are mentioned in
                            the letter text or who are correspondence partners (see table
                            below).</p>
                        <div>
                            <head type="h5">Parameters</head>
                            <div>
                                <head type="h5"><hi rend="code">type</hi></head>
                                <table rend="drawn" rows="2" cols="2">
                                    <row role="label">
                                        <cell>Values</cell>
                                        <cell>Description</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><hi rend="code">[not set]</hi></cell>
                                        <cell>all records in the persons register; set by default
                                            unless otherwise specified</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><hi rend="code">correspondents</hi></cell>
                                        <cell>all correspondents</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><hi rend="code">personMentioned</hi></cell>
                                        <cell>all persons mentioned</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head type="h5"><hi rend="code">authority</hi></head>
                                <p>all persons with a norm ID of a specific norm file (restricted by
                                        <hi rend="code">type</hi> if necessary)</p>
                                <table rend="drawn" rows="2" cols="2">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>value</cell>
                                        <cell>Description</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><hi rend="code">gnd</hi></cell>
                                        <cell>Common standards file of the German National Library;
                                            set by default unless otherwise specified</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell><hi rend="code">viaf</hi></cell>
                                        <cell>Virtual International Authority File</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head type="h4">Context Objects in span (COinS) &amp; Zotero API</head>
                        <p>The entries of the bibliography are also accessible via APIs. On the one
                            hand, they are embedded as machine-readable <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20140913071820/http://ocoins.info/">ContextObjects in spans</ref> in the HTML page of <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi>. This allows them to be
                            transferred directly into common literature management systems at the
                            click of a mouse. On the other hand, the complete biography is also
                            accessible as a publicly viewable Zotero group via the <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/support/dev/web_api/v3/basics">Zotero
                                API</ref> at <ref target="https://api.zotero.org/groups/667230/items">https://api.zotero.org/groups/667230/items</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head type="h2">Versioning, permalinks and citation notes</head>
                <p>The texts and data made available in <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt
                        digital</hi> are versioned, i.e. each published version (usually one per
                    year) of the content is kept available for retrieval. The entire published data
                    stock is always versioned. Thus, the register entries also reflect the links of
                    the respective version (cf. e.g. the entry on Georg Forster in <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/v1/H0000177?l=en">version 1</ref> compared to
                        <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/v9/H0000177?l=en">version 9</ref>). An
                    overview of the changes between the versions of <hi rendition="#i">edition
                        humboldt digital</hi> is provided by the <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/about/index.xql?id=H0020382&amp;l=en">version history</ref> introduced with version 8. It also evaluates the
                    number of pages edited, chronology and register entries created, and entity
                    links coded. </p>
                <p>All texts are provided with a citation note as well as permalinks that reference
                    the respective version (e.g.: <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/v1/H0002656?l=en">http://edition-humboldt.de/v1/H0002656;</ref> on citation and referencing
                    in digital editions, see <bibl corresp="https://edition-humboldt.de/TP6JVM4Q">Bleier
                        2021</bibl>). If necessary, the respective folio can also be referenced for
                    edited texts by simply adding the folio information to the path, e.g. <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/v9/H0002656/2v">https://edition-humboldt.de/v9/H0002656/2v</ref>. Research articles that do
                    not have page numbers due to their "digital born" character can be cited
                    paragraph by paragraph. For this purpose, the paragraph number (which is always
                    displayed at the top left of each paragraph) is appended as a so-called fragment
                    identifier with a #, e.g. <ref target="https://edition-humboldt.de/v9/H0016432#3">https://edition-humboldt.de/v9/H0016432#3</ref>. In addition to the texts
                    and register entries, certain subsections (main topics and various
                    correspondences), which - like a volume - are actually composed of several
                    texts, are also provided with their own citation notes including permalinks
                    (e.g. https://edition-humboldt.de/X0000003).</p>
                <p>In addition, the individual texts and data sets are also provided with a
                    canonical URL that always redirects to the most current version. This simply
                    omits the version reference in the path, e. <ref target="http://edition-humboldt.de/H0002656?l=en">g</ref>.
                    http://edition-humboldt.de/H0002656.</p>
                <p>The canonical and uniform URLs ("H" and a seven-digit number) have also made it
                    possible for the printed volumes of <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt</hi>
                    print to link back to the digital counterpart for edited texts.</p>
                <p>The interface itself, i.e. the XQL, XSLT and JS scripts as well as CSS and other
                    files, is currently not publicly versioned. However, it is versioned and kept in
                    a git for development purposes. For the future, it is also planned to store each
                    version of the digital edition (as a user interface) additionally in the <ref target="https://webarchive.bbaw.de/">web archive of the BBAW</ref> and to
                    keep it there. The <hi rendition="#i">edition humboldt digital</hi> is currently
                    being technically prepared so that it can be archived in the best possible
                    way.</p>
                <p>Independently of this, the data will also be published and archived permanently
                    on Zenodo (see section "Data publication").</p>
            </div>
        </body></text>
</TEI>